Gilbert Miller Collection
Music Division, Library of Congress
Guides to Special Collections in the Music Division of the Library of Congress
Gilbert Miller Collection 1921-1967 (bulk 1932-1955)
ML31.M55
Miller, Gilbert
4000 items 8 containers 4.0 linear feet
Music Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
This collection consists principally of theater production materials related to the life and activities of producer and theater owner Gilbert Miller (1884-1969). It includes correspondence, speeches, scripts, photographs, programs and clippings that convey Miller’s theatrical influences, personal connections, and professional accomplishments.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Abbott, George, 1887-1995.; Adler, Stella.; Anouilh, Jean, 1910-1987.; Atkinson, Brooks, 1894-1984.; Beaumont, Hugh, 1908-1973.; Behrman, S. N. (Samuel Nathaniel), 1893-1973.; Berlin, Irving, 1888-1989.; Bowes, Edward, Major, 1874-1946.; Claire, Ina, 1892-1985.; Coward, Noel, 1899-1973.; Cronyn, Hume.; Dalrymple, Jean.; Darvas, Lilli, d. 1974.; De Liagre, Alfred, 1904-1987.; De Nobili, Lila, 1916-2002.; Deval, Jacques, 1890-1972.; Gielgud, John, 1904-2000.; Gordon, Max, 1892-1978.; Hammerstein, Oscar, 1895-1960.; Harrison, Rex.; Hayes, Helen, 1900-1993.; Hayward, Leland, 1902-1971.; Hellman, Lillian, 1905-1984.; Howard, Sidney Coe, 1891-1939.; Kaufman, George S. (George Simon), 1889-1961.; Kazan, Elia.; Kostelanetz, Andre, 1901-1980.; Lawrence, Gertrude.; Lewis, Robert, 1909-1997.; Loos, Anita, 1893-1981.; Merivale, John, 1917-1990.; Merrick, David, 1911-2000.; Miller, Gilbert--Correspondence.; Miller, Gilbert.; Miller, Gilbert.; Morley, Robert.; Nesbitt, Cathleen, 1888-1982.; Olivier, Laurence, 1907-1989.; Ratoff, Gregory, 1897-1960.; Redgrave, Michael, Sir.; Rodgers, Richard, 1902-1979.; Schmidt, Lars, 1917-2009.; Shubert, Lee, 1873?-1953.; Tandy, Jessica.; Todd, Michael, 1909-1958.; Whistler, Rex, 1905-1944.; Whitehead, Robert, 1916-2002.
Organizations
Actors' Equity Association.; Henry Miller's Theatre (Organization: New York, N.Y.)
Subjects
Costume.; Musical theater--Production and direction.; Theater--Production and direction.; Theatrical producers and directors--Great Britain.; Theatrical producers and directors--United States.; Tony Awards.
Form/Genre
Correspondence.; Drawings (Visual works); Floor plans.; Photographs.; Playbills.; Scripts (Documents); Theater programs.
Administrative Information
Provenance
Purchase, from Joseph Robinette, 2004. Additional materials purchased in 2008.
Accruals
No further accruals are expected.
Access and Restrictions
The Gilbert Miller Collection is open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Performing Arts Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use. Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1884 July 3 Born in New York to actor-manager Henry Miller and actress Bijou Heron
1907 Begins theater management career as company manager of Henry Miller’s touring production of The Great Divide
1910-1915 Manages all of Henry Miller’s American productions
1916 Debuts as producer in London with Daddy Long-Legs
[ca. 1914-1918] Serves for three years in intelligence as a lieutenant in the U.S. Marine Corps and becomes part of the American Expeditionary Force during the First World War
1919 Opens first New York show, Monsieur Beacuaire
1921 June Takes over operation of the Empire Theatre and the Frohman Corporation
1932 Apr. Leaves Frohman Inc.
[ca. 1939-1944] Serves as an aircraft technician aboard the aircraft carrier Shangri-La during the Second World War
1950 The Cocktail Party wins Tony Award for Best Play
1958 The Rope Dancer nominated for Tony Award for Best Play
1962 The Caretaker nominated for Tony Award for Best Play
1965 Receives special Tony Award “For having produced 88 plays and musicals and for his perseverance which has helped to keep New York and theatre alive”
1968 Sells Henry Miller’s Theatre
1969 Jan. 2 Dies and is buried in Woodlawn Cemetery, New York
PRODUCTIONS: Polly with a past (1921), The nervous wreck (1924), The captive (1926), Dantons Tod (1927), Her cardboard lover (1927), Interference (1927), Midsummer night’s dream (1927), Jedermann (1927), Er ist an allem Schuld [He is to blame for everything] (1928), Diener zweier Herren [Servant of two masters] (1928), Kabale und Liebe (1928), The patriot (1928, Jan. 20, Jan. 29), Der lebende Leichnam [The living corpse] (1928), Olympia (1928), The sacred flame (1928), Our betters (1928), Peripherie (1928), Happy husband (1928), Paris (1928), The age of innocence (1928), Candle-light (1929), Love duel (1929), The skyrocket (1929), Journey’s end (1929), Hundred years old (1929), Berkeley Square (1929), Marseilles (1930, Nov. 9, Nov. 18), Petticoat influence (1930), Journey’s end (1930, Aug. 5, Aug. 24), The violet (1930), Tomorrow and tomorrow (1931), The sex fable (1931, Nov. 15, Nov. 25), The good fairy (1931), The animal kingdom (1932, Jan. 3, Jan. 13), Behold we live (1932), The late Christopher Bean (1932), Firebird (1932, Sept. 25, Nov. 22), This side idolatry (1933), Reunion in Vienna (1934), Bride of Torozko (1934, July 10, Sept. 14), Ode to liberty (1934 Dec. 11, Dec. 22), The petrified forest (1934), The petrified forest (1935), Laburnum grove (1935), The ringmaster (1935), Tovarich (1935), Libel! (1935, Dec. 3, Dec. 8, Dec. 21), Victoria Regina (1935, Dec. 13, Dec. 27), The country wife (1936, Oct. 7, Dec. 2), Pride and prejudice (1936), Tovarich (1936, Oct. 16, Oct. 25), Promise (1936), The amazing Dr. Clitterhouse (1937), Yes, my darling daughter (1937), Old music (1937), French without tears (1937, Sept. 26, Sept. 29), Victoria Regina (1937), Silent knight (1937), Murder in the cathedral (1938), Once is enough (1938), Victoria Regina (1938), I have been here before (1938), Ladies and gentlemen (1939), Geneva (1940), Ladies in retirement (1940), Delicate story (1940), Twelfth night (1940, Oct. 18, Oct. 27), Anne of England (1941), Lily of the valley (1942), Heart of a city (1942), Lifeline (1942), Flare path (1942), Harriet (1943, Mar. 4, Mar. 14), For keeps (1944), Harriet (1944), The rich full life (1945), Antigone (1946), Dear Ruth (1946), Candida (1946), Play’s the thing (1948, Apr. 29, May 9), Edward, my son (1948), Montserrat (1949), Cocktail party (1950), Ring around the moon (1950), Caesar and Cleopatra (1951), Antony and Cleopatra (1951), Horses in midstream (1953), The living room (1954), Witness for the prosecution (1954), The reluctant debutante (1956), The sleeping prince (1956), Under Milk Wood (1957), The rope dancer (1957), Look after Lulu (1959), Golden fleecing (1959), The caretaker (1961), The White House (1964), Diamond orchid (1965)
Scope and Content Note
The Gilbert Miller Collection spans the period 1921-1967. The bulk of the materials date from 1932-1955. The collection includes correspondence, contracts, scripts, speeches, scenic floor plans, scenic and costume renderings, clippings, programs, and other materials related to Gilbert Miller’s life and career. As a representation of Miller’s distinguished career, the materials provide insights into his work as a manager, producer, and advocate for the theater.
Organization of the Gilbert Miller Collection
The Gilbert Miller Collection is organized into 7 series:
Correspondence, 1921-1967 (1.75 linear feet)
Speeches, 1931, 1955 (1 folder)
Scripts (1 folder)
Photographs (.75 linear feet)
Technical-related Materials, 1937-1953 (.25 linear feet)
Programs (.75 linear feet)
Miscellaneous (.25 linear feet)
http://lccn.loc.gov/2006560744
Container List
- Correspondence, 1921-1967 (Box 1-4)
  The Correspondence series consists of business and personal correspondence to and from Miller. It includes contracts, telegraphs, and intra-office memos pertinent to Miller’s endeavors. Prominent correspondents include Jean Anouilh, Helen Hayes, Elia Kazan, Laurence Olivier, Gregory Ratoff, and Lee Shubert.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1921-1925 (Box-folder 1/1-5)
  - 1926-1930 (Box-folder 1/6-12)
  - 1931-1935 (Box-folder 1/11-15)
  - 1936-1939 (Box-folder 2/1-4)
  - 1940-1943 (Box-folder 2/5-8)
  - 1944-1948 (Box-folder 3/1-5)
  - 1949-1952 (Box-folder 3/6-9)
  - 1953-1959 (Box-folder 4/1-5)
  - 1960-1967 (Box-folder 4/6)
  - Undated (Box-folder 4/7)
- Speeches, 1931, 1955 (Box 4)
  The Speeches series consists of an annotated draft of a 1931 speech on the history of the Empire Theatre as well as a draft of an autobiographical speech commemorating the twentieth anniversary of Cue magazine in 1955.
  - Annotated drafts of "Talk on the history of the Empire Theatre, 1921-1925" (Box-folder 4/8)
  - Autobiographical speech commemorating the twentieth anniversary of Cue magazine, 1955 (Box-folder 4/8)
- Scripts (Box 4)
  The Scripts series contains five script synopses and one draft.
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
  - Brighton rock, Synopsis (Box-folder 4/9)
  - L’invitation au chateau [Ring round the moon] by Jean Anouilh, Annotated draft (Box-folder 4/9)
- Photographs (Box 5-6)
  The Photographs series provides images and information that contextualize the written records of Miller’s life and career. It includes production and candid photos.
  Arranged alphabetically by show title.
  - Productions by or related to G. Miller (Box 5-6)
    - Anne of England, 1941, 45 black and white photographs (Box-folder 5/1)
    - Caesar and Cleopatra, 1951, 4 black and white photographs (Box-folder 5/2)
    - The cocktail party, 1950, 12 black and white photographs (Box-folder 5/3)
    - Delicate story, 1940, 2 black and white photographs (Box-folder 5/4)
    - Edward, my son, 1948, 16 black and white photographs and 36 black and white proof sheets (Box-folder 5/5)
    - Flare path, 1942, 25 black and white photographs (Box-folder 5/6)
    - Gigi, 1951, 14 black and white photographs (Box-folder 5/7)
    - Harriet, 1943/1944, 1 color and 18 black and white photographs (Box-folder 5/8)
    - Ladies in retirement, 1940, 17 black and white photographs (Box-folder 5/9)
    - Old music, 1937, 1 black and white photographs (Box-folder 5/10)
    - Ring round the moon, 1950, 30 black and white photographs and one page from Theatre World, 1950 Mar. (Box-folder 5/11)
    - The sleeping prince, 1953, 6 black and white photographs (Box-folder 5/12)
    - Victoria Regina, 1951, 1 color and 1 black and white photograph (Box-folder 6/1)
    - The voice of the turtle, 1947, 3 black and white proof sheets (Box-folder 6/2)
    - Gilbert Miller, individually or with others, 1 color and 3 black and white photographs (Box-folder 6/3)
    - Miscellaneous, 14 black and white photographs and 1 clipping from the Cleveland Plain Dealer, 1944 Mar. 5 (Box-folder 6/4)
  - Productions not related to G. Miller (Box 6)
    - An ideal husband, 1944, 3 black and white photographs (Box-folder 6/5)
    - My fair lady, 1981, 47 black and white photographs (Box-folder 6/6)
- Technical-related Materials, 1937-1953 (Box 6)
  The Technical-related materials series provides images and information that contextualize the written records of Miller’s life and career. It includes floor plans, paint and fabric samples, and scenic and costume renderings.
  - The cocktail party, 1950 (Box-folder 6/7)
  - Harriet, 1943/1944 (Box-folder 6/8)
  - Gigi, 1953 (Box-folder 6/9)
  - An ideal husband, 1944 (Box-folder 6/10)
  - Ring round the moon, 1950 (Box-folder 6/11)
  - Miscellaneous (Box-folder 6/12)
  - Unidentified scenic rendering (Box-folder OV 1)
- Programs (Box 6-8)
  The Programs series consists of 183 programs and playbills, chiefly from Miller productions, that highlight his unique professional relationships with various collaborators, casts, and sponsors.
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Productions by or related to G. Miller, 1929-1954 (Box 6-7)
    - A-B (Box-folder 6/13)
    - C (Box-folder 6/14)
    - D-E (Box-folder 7/1)
    - F-G (Box-folder 7/2)
    - H-K (Box-folder 7/3)
    - L (Box-folder 7/4)
    - M-Q (Box-folder 7/5)
    - R-T (Box-folder 7/6)
    - U-V (Box-folder 7/7)
    - W-Z (Box-folder 7/8)
  - Productions not related to G. Miller (Box 7-8)
    - A-D (Box-folder 7/9)
    - E-L (Box-folder 7/10)
    - M-R (Box-folder 8/1)
    - S-Z (Box-folder 8/2)
- Miscellaneous (Box 8)
  The Miscellaneous series is a collection of diverse items that are largely tied to Miller’s theatrical career and business endeavors. It also contains positive and negative correspondence from various individuals concerning the one-year anniversary party for producer Michael Todd’s film Around the World in 80 Days. It is unclear how this material relates directly to Miller.
  Arranged alphabetically by topic.
  - Around the world in 80 days, Correspondence related to Michael Todd’s one-year anniversary party for the film (Box-folder 8/3-5)
  - Caricature on back of restaurant placemat (Box-folder 8/6)
  - Dramatist Guild handbook, Inscribed to Miller from George Middleton (Box-folder 8/6)
  - The Empire Tatler, No. 4, 1929 Aug. (Box-folder 8/6)
  - Harriet, annotated advertisement (Box-folder 8/6)
  - Lily of the valley “Sonnet to the cast” (Box-folder 8/6)
  - Louis Jouvet program, ca. 1951 (Box-folder 8/6)
  - Make it last long (from For Keeps) sheet music, Inscribed to Miller (Box-folder 8/6)
  - My Lord, what a mornin’ sheet music, Inscribed to Miller by H. T. Burleigh? (Box-folder 8/6)
  - Over land and over sea sheet music, Annotated, with signed letter from Alexander Seversky (Box-folder 8/6)
  - Passport, ca. 1922 (Box-folder 8/6)
  - Passport, ca. 1924 (Box-folder 8/6)
  - Pocket calendar, 1939 Jan.-Feb. (Box-folder 8/6)
  - Victoria Regina tour booklet (Box-folder 8/6)
  - While parents sleep souvenir handkerchief (Box-folder 8/6)